وَيَوْمَ يُحْشَرُ أَعْدَاءُ اللَّهِ إِلَى النَّارِ فَهُمْ يُوزَعُونَ - 41:19
And [mention, O Muhammad], the Day when the enemies of Allah will be gathered to the Fire while they are [driven] assembled in rows,
حَتَّىٰ إِذَا مَا جَاءُوهَا شَهِدَ عَلَيْهِمْ سَمْعُهُمْ
Until, when they reach it, their hearing will testify against them
شَهِدَ عَلَيْهِمْ سَمْعُهُمْ وَأَبْصَارُهُمْ وَجُلُودُهُم بِمَا كَانُوا يَعْمَلُونَ - 41:20
their hearing and their eyes and their skins will testify against them of what they used to do.
وَقَالُوا لِجُلُودِهِمْ لِمَ شَهِدتُّمْ عَلَيْنَا ۖ
And they will say to their skins, "Why have you testified against us?"
قَالُوا أَنطَقَنَا اللَّهُ
They will say, "We were made to speak by Allah,
قَالُوا أَنطَقَنَا اللَّهُ الَّذِي أَنطَقَ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ وَهُوَ خَلَقَكُمْ أَوَّلَ مَرَّةٍ
They will say, "We were made to speak by Allah, who has made everything speak; and He created you the first time,
وَهُوَ خَلَقَكُمْ أَوَّلَ مَرَّةٍ وَإِلَيْهِ تُرْجَعُونَ - 41:21
and He created you the first time, and to Him you are returned.
وَمَا كُنتُمْ تَسْتَتِرُونَ أَن يَشْهَدَ عَلَيْكُمْ سَمْعُكُمْ وَلَا أَبْصَارُكُمْ وَلَا جُلُودُكُمْ وَلَٰكِن
And you were not covering yourselves, lest your hearing testify against you or your sight or your skins, but
وَلَٰكِن ظَنَنتُمْ أَنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يَعْلَمُ كَثِيرًا مِّمَّا تَعْمَلُونَ - 41:22
but you assumed that Allah does not know much of what you do.
وَذَٰلِكُمْ ظَنُّكُمُ الَّذِي ظَنَنتُم بِرَبِّكُمْ أَرْدَاكُمْ فَأَصْبَحْتُم مِّنَ الْخَاسِرِينَ - 41:23
And that was your assumption which you assumed about your Lord. It has brought you to ruin, and you have become among the losers."
فَإِن يَصْبِرُوا فَالنَّارُ مَثْوًى لَّهُمْ ۖ
So [even] if they are patient, the Fire is a residence for them;
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم
I seek refuge in Allah from the cursed Satan
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
In the name of Allah, The All-Merciful, The Ever-Merciful
قُلْ أَئِنَّكُمْ لَتَكْفُرُونَ بِالَّذِي خَلَقَ الْأَرْضَ فِي يَوْمَيْنِ وَتَجْعَلُونَ لَهُ أَندَادًا ۚ
Say, "Do you indeed disbelieve in He who created the earth in two days and attribute to Him equals?
ذَٰلِكَ رَبُّ الْعَالَمِينَ - 41:9
That is the Lord of the worlds."
وَجَعَلَ فِيهَا رَوَاسِيَ مِن فَوْقِهَا وَبَارَكَ فِيهَا وَقَدَّرَ فِيهَا أَقْوَاتَهَا
And He placed on the earth firmly set mountains over its surface, and He blessed it and determined therein its [creatures'] sustenance
وَقَدَّرَ فِيهَا أَقْوَاتَهَا فِي أَرْبَعَةِ أَيَّامٍ سَوَاءً لِّلسَّائِلِينَ - 41:10
and determined therein its [creatures'] sustenance in four days without distinction - for [the information] of those who ask.
ثُمَّ اسْتَوَىٰ إِلَى السَّمَاءِ وَهِيَ دُخَانٌ فَقَالَ لَهَا وَلِلْأَرْضِ ائْتِيَا طَوْعًا أَوْ كَرْهًا
Then He directed Himself to the heaven while it was smoke and said to it and to the earth, "Come [into being], willingly or by compulsion."
قَالَتَا أَتَيْنَا طَائِعِينَ - 41:11
They said, "We have come willingly."
فَقَضَاهُنَّ سَبْعَ سَمَاوَاتٍ فِي يَوْمَيْنِ وَأَوْحَىٰ فِي كُلِّ سَمَاءٍ أَمْرَهَا ۚ
And He completed them as seven heavens within two days and inspired in each heaven its command.
وَزَيَّنَّا السَّمَاءَ الدُّنْيَا بِمَصَابِيحَ وَحِفْظًا ۚ ذَٰلِكَ تَقْدِيرُ الْعَزِيزِ الْعَلِيمِ - 41:12
And We adorned the nearest heaven with lamps and as protection. That is the determination of the Exalted in Might, the Knowing.
فَإِنْ أَعْرَضُوا فَقُلْ أَنذَرْتُكُمْ صَاعِقَةً مِّثْلَ صَاعِقَةِ عَادٍ وَثَمُودَ - 41:13
But if they turn away, then say, "I have warned you of a thunderbolt like the thunderbolt [that struck] 'Aad and Thamud.
إِذْ جَاءَتْهُمُ الرُّسُلُ مِن بَيْنِ أَيْدِيهِمْ وَمِنْ خَلْفِهِمْ أَلَّا تَعْبُدُوا إِلَّا اللَّهَ ۖ
[That occurred] when the messengers had come to them before them and after them, [saying], "Worship not except Allah ."
قَالُوا لَوْ شَاءَ رَبُّنَا لَأَنزَلَ مَلَائِكَةً فَإِنَّا بِمَا أُرْسِلْتُم بِهِ كَافِرُونَ - 41:14
They said, "If our Lord had willed, He would have sent down the angels, so indeed we, in that with which you have been sent, are disbelievers."
فَأَمَّا عَادٌ فَاسْتَكْبَرُوا فِي الْأَرْضِ بِغَيْرِ الْحَقِّ وَقَالُوا مَنْ أَشَدُّ مِنَّا قُوَّةً ۖ
As for 'Aad, they were arrogant upon the earth without right and said, "Who is greater than us in strength?"
أَوَلَمْ يَرَوْا أَنَّ اللَّهَ الَّذِي خَلَقَهُمْ هُوَ أَشَدُّ مِنْهُمْ قُوَّةً ۖ
Did they not consider that Allah who created them was greater than them in strength?
وَكَانُوا بِآيَاتِنَا يَجْحَدُونَ - 41:15
But they were rejecting Our signs.
فَأَرْسَلْنَا عَلَيْهِمْ رِيحًا صَرْصَرًا فِي أَيَّامٍ نَّحِسَاتٍ لِّنُذِيقَهُمْ
So We sent upon them a screaming wind during days of misfortune to make them taste ..
لِّنُذِيقَهُمْ عَذَابَ الْخِزْيِ فِي الْحَيَاةِ الدُّنْيَا ۖ
to make them taste the punishment of disgrace in the worldly life;
وَلَعَذَابُ الْآخِرَةِ أَخْزَىٰ ۖ وَهُمْ لَا يُنصَرُونَ - 41:16
but the punishment of the Hereafter is more disgracing, and they will not be helped.
وَأَمَّا ثَمُودُ فَهَدَيْنَاهُمْ فَاسْتَحَبُّوا الْعَمَىٰ عَلَى الْهُدَىٰ
And as for Thamud, We guided them, but they preferred blindness over guidance,
فَاسْتَحَبُّوا الْعَمَىٰ عَلَى الْهُدَىٰ فَأَخَذَتْهُمْ صَاعِقَةُ الْعَذَابِ الْهُونِ بِمَا كَانُوا يَكْسِبُونَ - 41:17
but they preferred blindness over guidance, so the thunderbolt of humiliating punishment seized them for what they used to earn.
وَنَجَّيْنَا الَّذِينَ آمَنُوا وَكَانُوا يَتَّقُونَ - 41:18
And We saved those who believed and used to fear Allah .
وَيَوْمَ يُحْشَرُ أَعْدَاءُ اللَّهِ إِلَى النَّارِ فَهُمْ يُوزَعُونَ - 41:19
And [mention, O Muhammad], the Day when the enemies of Allah will be gathered to the Fire while they are [driven] assembled in rows,
حَتَّىٰ إِذَا مَا جَاءُوهَا شَهِدَ عَلَيْهِمْ سَمْعُهُمْ
Until, when they reach it, their hearing will testify against them
شَهِدَ عَلَيْهِمْ سَمْعُهُمْ وَأَبْصَارُهُمْ وَجُلُودُهُم بِمَا كَانُوا يَعْمَلُونَ - 41:20
their hearing and their eyes and their skins will testify against them of what they used to do.
وَقَالُوا لِجُلُودِهِمْ لِمَ شَهِدتُّمْ عَلَيْنَا ۖ
And they will say to their skins, "Why have you testified against us?"
قَالُوا أَنطَقَنَا اللَّهُ
They will say, "We were made to speak by Allah,
قَالُوا أَنطَقَنَا اللَّهُ الَّذِي أَنطَقَ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ وَهُوَ خَلَقَكُمْ أَوَّلَ مَرَّةٍ
They will say, "We were made to speak by Allah, who has made everything speak; and He created you the first time,
وَهُوَ خَلَقَكُمْ أَوَّلَ مَرَّةٍ وَإِلَيْهِ تُرْجَعُونَ - 41:21
and He created you the first time, and to Him you are returned.
وَمَا كُنتُمْ تَسْتَتِرُونَ أَن يَشْهَدَ عَلَيْكُمْ سَمْعُكُمْ وَلَا أَبْصَارُكُمْ وَلَا جُلُودُكُمْ وَلَٰكِن
And you were not covering yourselves, lest your hearing testify against you or your sight or your skins, but
وَلَٰكِن ظَنَنتُمْ أَنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يَعْلَمُ كَثِيرًا مِّمَّا تَعْمَلُونَ - 41:22
but you assumed that Allah does not know much of what you do.
وَذَٰلِكُمْ ظَنُّكُمُ الَّذِي ظَنَنتُم بِرَبِّكُمْ أَرْدَاكُمْ فَأَصْبَحْتُم مِّنَ الْخَاسِرِينَ - 41:23
And that was your assumption which you assumed about your Lord. It has brought you to ruin, and you have become among the losers."
فَإِن يَصْبِرُوا فَالنَّارُ مَثْوًى لَّهُمْ ۖ
So [even] if they are patient, the Fire is a residence for them;
وَإِن يَسْتَعْتِبُوا فَمَا هُم مِّنَ الْمُعْتَبِينَ - 41:24
and if they ask to appease [ Allah ], they will not be of those who are allowed to appease.
وَقَيَّضْنَا لَهُمْ قُرَنَاءَ فَزَيَّنُوا لَهُم مَّا بَيْنَ أَيْدِيهِمْ وَمَا خَلْفَهُمْ
And We appointed for them companions who made attractive to them what was before them and what was behind them [of sin],
وَحَقَّ عَلَيْهِمُ الْقَوْلُ فِي أُمَمٍ قَدْ خَلَتْ مِن قَبْلِهِم مِّنَ الْجِنِّ وَالْإِنسِ ۖ
and the word has come into effect upon them among nations which had passed on before them of jinn and men.
إِنَّهُمْ كَانُوا خَاسِرِينَ - 41:25
Indeed, they [all] were losers.